<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Church-members set in joynt. Or, A discovery of the unwarrantable and disorderly practice of private Christians, in usurping the peculiar office and work of Christs own pastours, namely publike preaching. In way of answer to a book printed under the name of Lieutenant Edmund Chillenden (but indeed none of his) entituled Preaching without ordination. Wherein all the arguments by him produced, are fully answered and disproved, the truth of the contrary evidenced, and the office forementioned, thereby returned into the hands of the right owners. / By Filodexter Transilvanus.</title>
            <author>Woodbridge, Benjamin, 1622-1684.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1648</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 93 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A96865</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W3423</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E422_3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R204785</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99864247</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99864247</idno>
            <idno type="VID">116472</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A96865)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 116472)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 66:E422[3])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Church-members set in joynt. Or, A discovery of the unwarrantable and disorderly practice of private Christians, in usurping the peculiar office and work of Christs own pastours, namely publike preaching. In way of answer to a book printed under the name of Lieutenant Edmund Chillenden (but indeed none of his) entituled Preaching without ordination. Wherein all the arguments by him produced, are fully answered and disproved, the truth of the contrary evidenced, and the office forementioned, thereby returned into the hands of the right owners. / By Filodexter Transilvanus.</title>
                  <author>Woodbridge, Benjamin, 1622-1684.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 32 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Edmund Paxton, and are to be sold at his shop in Pauls chain, over against the Castle Tavern neer to the Doctors Commons,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1648.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Filodexter Transilvanus = Benjamin Woodbridge.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Jan. 5"; the "8" in the imprint has been crossed out and replaced with a "7".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Chillenden, Edmund, fl. 1656. --  Preaching without ordination --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Lay preaching --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:116472:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:116472:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Church-Members SET IN JOYNT.</p>
            <p>OR, A Diſcovery of the unwarrantable and diſorderly practice of private chriſtians, in uſurping the peculiar Office and work of Chriſts own Paſtours, namely PUBLIKE PREACHING.</p>
            <p>In way of Anſwer to a Book printed under the name of Lieutenant <hi>Edmund Chillenden</hi> (but indeed none of his) entituled <hi>Preaching without Ordination.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherein all the Arguments by him produced, are fully Anſwered and diſproved, the truth of the contrary evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denced, and the Office forementioned, thereby returned into the hands of the right owners.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Filodexter Tranſilvanus.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 5. 4.</bibl> No man taketh this honour to himſelf, but he that is called of God, as was <hi>Aaron.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Jer.</hi> 23. 21.</bibl> I have not ſent theſe Prophets, yet they ran: I have not ſpoken to them, yet they propheſied.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Matth.</hi> 7. 15.</bibl> Beware of falſe Prophets, which come to you in Sheeps cloth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, but inwardly they are ravening Wolves.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for EDMUND PAXTON, and are to be ſold at his Shop in <hi>Pauls</hi> chain, over againſt the Caſtle Tavern neer to the Doctors Commons. 1648.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:116472:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:116472:2"/>
            <head>To all the faithfull in Chriſt Jeſus, and all other my Country-men, who may chance at any time to be Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of this Book.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>BRETHREN,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y hearts deſire and prayer to God for you all is, that you may be ſaved, and that you may bee rooted and eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed in the faith of that Chriſt and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel which you have received, and by which alſo you are ſaved, if you conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue ſtedfaſt unto the end, &amp; be not removed from him that hath called you into the grace of Chriſt, to give ear to ſeducers and falſe prophets, who pervert the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel of Chriſt, and ſubvert the faith of many. Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onleſſe the dayes are come upon us, of which our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our hath foretold us long ago, that many falſe prophets ſhall ariſe, and deceive many; yea (if it were poſſible) the very elect themſeles: who may therefore the more abundantly rejoyce in this confidence that God will keep them by his owne power through faith unto ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation; when they ſhall perceive themſelves planted upon a rock that is higher then the gates of hell,
<pb facs="tcp:116472:3"/> ſtronger then the raine and tempeſts that aſſault them: by the power of which they are enabled to ſtand, even in ſuch times as theſe (which are the worſt of times) when ſo many hundreds fall on the right hand and on the left. Amongſt many other meanes which God (J doubt not) will teach you to make uſe of for your continuance in the faith: the matter of this enſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Treatiſe gives me occaſion to ſpeak of one, which is a high priſing of and diligent attendance upon the miniſtry, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he word: that word I meane which is preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by thoſe who are ſent of God and this Church for the ſame purpoſe. In my ſhort experience I have obſerved that the Divells grand deſigne for the raiſing of his own Kingdome, hath beene in all ages to hinder the efficacie and authority of the publik Miniſtry. In the daies of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſtian darkneſſe there was either no preaching at all, or none but that which was delivered in a ſtrange language, by which the people received no benefit. In latter dayes, under the Prelates tyranny here in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, what ſtone was left unrolled to diſcourage and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dermine the moſt ſaithſull, holy and learned miniſters: either by withholding from them a competent mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance (whiles many a prophane ſuperſtitious dotard and dumbe dogge had more then enough) or by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyning an ungodly compliance to humane and anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian inventions, Ceremonies, Oathes, Subſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, &amp;c. which their conſciences could not away with: Hence many profeſſors made it the greateſt part of their religion, and made this their reſt, even to goe up and downe, to heare Sermons, and ſpeak againſt thoſe (perſons or things) that were the occaſion of muzling the mouthes of ſo many of Gods meſſengers. In theſe
<pb facs="tcp:116472:3"/> dayes the doore is opened ſo wide, that who ſo will, may now take upon him that high and holy calling, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der pretence of preaching the Goſpel, vent privately and publikely all manner of untruths, and becauſe they cannot raiſe themſelves to that high pitch of preferment which they aime at, as long as godly Miniſters beare witneſſe againſt them both in Pulpits and Preſſes: therefore they poſſeſſe their Proſelites with all the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice they can againſt their Miniſters, either their calling is Antichriſtian, or they are men of an Old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſpirit, or (at beſt) they are Black-coats. Hence many, who have acknowledged often with much com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort that God had made their Miniſter inſtrumental, not onely to turne them firſt unto God, but to build them up in faith, and knowledge and all grace, and have for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meriy loved them ſo dearly that they could even have pulled out their eyes to have done them good: yet now they disfrequent their company and their Miniſtry: and lay themſelves open thereby to all manner of Temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and deluſions: and the farther they fall away, the higher they raiſe up themſelves in their owne eſteeme, giving forth that they are all taught of God: and hence they take upon them deſperatly to broach all manner of proud Atheiſtical conceits; one queſtions whether there be any Heaven or Hell, or any Reſurrection from the dead: another thinks himſelfe to be as good a Chriſt as Chriſt the Lord, and doth not fear to ſay that the God-head is as much in him as it was in Chriſt, &amp;c. whoſe diſtemper is the more deſpreate becauſe the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of it is to admit of no remedy. In the middeſt of this confuſion whether ſhall we fly? The Land is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come like ſome deepe pit in a wilderneſſe into which
<pb facs="tcp:116472:4"/> are fallen Toades, Mice, Frogs Serpents and all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of vermin, and there they bite and devoure one an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other: Religion is turned into a very gallimafra of errours and hereſies, and each hereſy brands all other doctrines with the name of Hereſie, beſides it ſelfe. The wiſe and eternall God which made the world out of a Chaos, and brought light out of darkneſſe, in his rich mercy bring light and order out of this diſmall hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh confuſion, and let all that love the Truth ſay Amen.</p>
            <p>In order to which end I have under-taken in this enſuing Treatiſe according to the ability I have receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, to make forth this truth againſt <hi>Chillenden</hi> and all his followers, that there is no ground either in reaſon or Scripture for private perſons, though never ſo well gifted, to preach publickly unleſſe they be thereto cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Church: intending ſhortly (if God permit) to prove poſitively from the Scriptures that preaching is a work peculiar to Church-officers. And before the Reader peruſe the Treatiſe it ſelfe, I ſhall deſire him to take notice of theſe two particulars.</p>
            <p>1. That al the arguments which I have here undertaken to anſwer, are ſtolen out of a Booke of <hi>Robinſons</hi> (the famous Separatiſt) entituled <hi>The peoples plea for prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſying.</hi> I believe <hi>Chillenden</hi> would be content that the child ſhould be divided; for if it be wholly given to the right father, upon my credit <hi>Chillenden</hi> muſt have no part in it.</p>
            <p>2. I have not taken notice of many places of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture written in the margin, but of thoſe onely to which he doth expreſſely referre his Reader: partly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are very unequally aſcribed, not paralell to
<pb facs="tcp:116472:4"/> the line to which they refer; and partly becauſe moſt of them are places from which he borrows words or phra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes occaſionally mentioned, nothing at all pertaining to the maine ſcope; many other things of leſſe conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence I have paſſed over, but nothing of moment as I know of. Farewell.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>F. T.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <p>Imprimatur,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Edm. Calamy.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:116472:5"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:116472:5"/>
            <head>An Anſwer to a Book entituled <hi>Preaching without Ordination.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Lieutenant, before he comes to ſpeak a word to the Queſtion by himſelfe propounded in the fore-front of his Book, <hi>viz. Whether men may Preach except they be Ordained:</hi> premiſeth many things to conſideration, which are neither of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny neceſſary dependance upon each other: nor of any uſe imaginable, either to the cleering and well ſtating of the Queſtion, or to the confirmation of his own opinion touching the Queſtion. For which reaſon I ſhall not now retreat ſo farre from the buſineſſe in hand, as to make an incurſion up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his <hi>praecognita</hi> (things which neither of us are concerned in, as to this preſent controverſie:) but ſhall there begin to anſwer where hee begins to make good his undertaking, after hee hath brought about the Queſtion (as it were by countermarch) into its former place, and applyes himſelfe to the proofe of the affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mative; namely, <hi>that it is lawfull for a perſon not ordained to Preach.</hi> Thus farre onely I ſhall follow him, as to make uſe of his method in premiſing ſome few Poſitions for the better ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of the Queſtion between him and mee.</p>
            <p>Firſt then I cannot but take notice that every one of his ſtolen Arguments, whereby hee labours to evince the lawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of preaching without Ordination, are of equall force to prove the lawfulneſſe of preaching without the Churches choyce and approbation: the thing wherein himſelfe and others of his way doe place the very eſſentials and vitals of a miniſter, as to any outward call, as may be ſeen in his poſitions Pag. 2: and 3. and then to what purpoſe is a Liberty of Chooſing their Miniſter given to every particular congregationall Church, as the thing whereby he is made a miniſter: ſeeing every private
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:116472:6"/> gifted Chriſtian, <hi>eo ipſo</hi> becauſe gifted, may take upon him to preach publikely though neither ordained nor yet Choſen by the Chruch? for ſuch an intrinſicall connexion doth this Author make between gifts and preaching, that, if his Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments be ſound there neede not intervene ſo much as the Chruches Election, nay farther, not ſo much as a tryall of thoſe miniſteriall gifts &amp; qualifications which himſelf acknowledgeth to be requiſites before a perſon be ordained, <hi>Theſ.</hi> 6. 2. I deſire the Reader to take notice, that when we preach for Ordination as a thing requiſite to a Preacher, we are to be underſtood ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Analogy of theſe following advertiſemntes.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That by Ordination we mean an act of the Church, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by a perſon is ſolemnly ſet apart for the diſpenſation of the word, Seales and Cenſures, by way of peculiar office: we doe therefore at this time wave all diſputes about the perſons or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daining, and all other rites and circumſtances pertaining to Ordination.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Preaching we take in the ſtricteſt ſenſe for an explication and application of the Word of God with all authority, to the information, exhortation, reproof or comfort of them that hear.</p>
            <p n="3">3 We acknowledge it a duty incombent upon all Chriſtians (whether eminently gifted or no) even the leaſt and meaneſt, to reprove, exhort, in ſtruct and comfort one another, as occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſhall be offered, in away of love, and of equall and mutuall intereſt, as members ſpiritually of one another, and heyres to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether of the kingdome of life.</p>
            <p n="4">4 In a Church that hath not its compleat conſtitution and organization (which <hi>Chillenden</hi> Calls a Church not perfectly brought under Goſpel order) or in other Caſes of abſolute neceſſity: we admit in reaſon of a liberty for private gifted Chriſtians to preach the word: though the Scripture hath nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther any particular precept for it, nor clear patterne of it, as I know of. Yet in no caſe can it be allowed that any private Chriſtian (though never ſo well gifted) ſhall take upon him to preach to any Church, unleſſe he have at leaſt the election and approbation of that Church: which we ſuppoſe to be a ſufficient outward call, when the Churches condition is (as it may be) ſuch, as that it is morally impoſſible to have a better. <hi>Jus divinum poſitivum, cedit juri divino naturali,</hi> when they are inconſiſtent each with other.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:116472:6"/>5 If any Chriſtian hath others in ſubjection under him, he hath thereby authority to inſtruct, reprove and exhort them out of the word of God. Men were made immediatly for God, immediatly for one another, or for one another in the Lord. Religion hath the command of all mens faculties, conditions, and actions, to referre and order them immediatly to Gods glory, that the whole man may live wholly unto God He muſt therfore live unto God in reſpect of his power over others: that is, his power over others muſt be ordered and improved to Gods glory, elſe he lives not wholly to God; Hence we grant, that a father or maſter in his family may inſtruct, exhort and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand his children and his houſehold to doe juſtice and judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. A King or Magiſtrate in the Common-wealth may exhort and command his ſubjects to the generall dutyes of Religion. For Religion refers all power to a Spirituall end. But ſome power is immediatly Spirituall, as the power of the Miniſters of the Goſpel, the immediate end or object whereof is the Spitituall good of their people. Other power is more remotely Spirituall, which though it ames at Spirituall good, yet it attaines it not but by the intervention of that power which is immediately Spirituall v. 8. The Magiſtrate ought to looke to the ſpirituall good of his people, therefore he may com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand them to give diligent attendance to the Word preached and to practiſe according to what is taught, and may make uſe of many perſwaſives and diſſuaſives as he thinks fit, which is as much as any of the Kings of Iſrael ever did in any of their inſtructions or publique exhortations to their people. The like may bee ſaid of all other power, domeſtique or military. Theſe things being premiſed, the truth I ſhall undertake to defend againſt Mr. <hi>Chillenden,</hi> is this,</p>
            <p>That it is utterly unlawfull for any Chriſtian whatſoever, gifted or not gifted, to take upon him ordinarily to Preach the Word in the name of the Lord with all authority before the Church publiquely aſſembled, unleſſe he be called and ſet apart thereto by the Church. Hereof I might bring proofe ſufficient: but my warre is at this time defenſive, not offenſive. Let us therefore try what ſtrength our adverſary is of.</p>
            <p>Having therefore firſt ſuppoſed that Churches have power to chooſe, yea and to Ordain (which is falſe) their own Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, he inferres thus.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:116472:7"/>
            <p>
               <label>Chill.</label> 
               <hi>If the Church have power, it muſt be granted that firſt there muſt bee a Church having this power, before there can be any Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers rightly ordained. Therefore, if men may not Preach before they be ordained, how can men be compleated to the Faith and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the Goſpel?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Anſw.</label> The meaning of this Argument I ſuppoſe is this, the Church is before the Miniſter. The Church is called by the Preaching of the Word; therefore ſome who were no Miniſters ordained, muſt neceſſarily be ſuppoſed to be Preachers; for without preaching no Church; and without a Church no ordained Officer. I liſt not now to take notice of every errour, onely in reference to the preſent controverſie, I anſwer, 1. The eldeſt Church had a Miniſter before it, as every effect hath its Cauſe before it; The firſt Churches were gathered by the Apoſtles, Prophets and Evangeliſts; who were men ordained and ſent of God for that purpoſe, <hi>John</hi> 5. 16. And being gathered, were by the Apoſtles themſelves commended to the care and watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe of ordinary Elders, <hi>Act.</hi> 20. 17, &amp; 28. Who were per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, not onely gifted, but ordained, <hi>Act. 14. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>3. Tit.</hi> 1. 5. that through the hand of God going along with them, Churches might bee edified, increaſed, multiplyed, unto the worlds end, <hi>Eph</hi> 4. 13. In ſucceſſion of ages there has been ſucceſſion of Churches, and ſucceſſion of Elders; but both the one and the other miſerably corrupted and defaced in the common deluge of Antichriſtianiſme. The way of Elders entring into their Office, we acknowledge to have been corrupt in all its circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, yet for the ſubſtance valid: as <hi>Caiaphas</hi> his entring up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Prieſthood in ſuch an irregular way, was unallowable, yet being entred, it ſtood, and God himſelfe, did not withold from him a Spirit of Propheſie, in the time of his Prieſthood, which was a common ſigne of confirmation given unto men that were called to any weighty and publique Office in <hi>Iſrael.</hi> But I perceive <hi>Chillenden</hi> aſcribes not much to this Argument, and therefore I have reaſon to ſay but little to it, eſpecially be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe learned men (ſuch as Mr. <hi>Rutherford</hi> and others) have ſaid ſo much to it in their late writings upon the controverſies of theſe times.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Chill.</label> Chil. His ſecond Argument in a word is this. <hi>It is lawfull for a man that intends the Miniſtery, to Preach before hee is or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:116472:7"/> for tryall.</hi> Ergo <hi>to Preach without Ordination is lawfull.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Anſw.</label> 
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> It is lawfull without all queſtion for a man that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends the publique Miniſtery to Preach for tryall before them that are to judge: but from hence to inferre, that every private man of what condition ſoever, who has no purpoſe nor inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to apply himſelfe wholly and onely to the work of the Miniſtery, may thruſt himſelfe upon a courſe of conſtant prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching publiquely, before the Church, without reference had to any tryall or judgement concerning his abilities, is wild reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. A man that Preaches for tryall is ſuppoſed to be called thereunto by the Church, by vertue of which call (if he accept of it) he is a Miniſter in <hi>fieri,</hi> though not in <hi>facto eſſe,</hi> and may therefore lawfully performe thoſe actions which tend to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat him in the execution of that charge which he is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring upon: all Miniſteriall actions he may not performe, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe he be Ordained (for ordination is that which gives com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleate Miniſteriall power) nor yet this ſingle act of Preaching can he performe, with ſuch authority, and confidence of Gods aſſiſtance, as after he is ordained, as 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. 14. For his Call being but imperfect, it can give him but an imperfect power: how beit whatſoever actions are conducible to the end of his Call (which is to give teſtimony concerning his abilities for the Miniſtery) thoſe he may performe, till by Ordination his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion be inlarged, and extended to all Miniſteriall actions. The ſons of the Prophets were wont to exerciſe their Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall gift, before they were generally received and acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged as Prophets. 1 <hi>Sam. 10. 5. 2 King.</hi> 2. 7. &amp;c. The Apoſtles and 70 Diſciples whom Chriſt ſent forth, <hi>Luke</hi> 10. 1. and <hi>Matth.</hi> 10. might do, and did many things by vertue of that Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion which then Chriſt gave them: yet thoſe things which he gave them in their laſt Commiſſion as Apoſtles, <hi>John</hi> 20. they neither did nor might doe when they were firſt ſent out; their Call did not reach to it. So a man that intends the Miniſtery and is called to give tryall of his gifts, may Preach in reference to that end, (which another may not) though he may not ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſter the Sacraments, nor yet make a continuall trade of Preaching.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Chill.</label> 
               <hi>But</hi> (ſayes Chillinden) <hi>if a man may Preach one Sermon, why not two, then why not twenty? And if one moneth, why not twelve moneths?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:116472:8"/>
            <p>Becauſe the Churches calling of him to Preach for tryall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a tranſient action, having order and reference to Ordination, as a more pefect and compleating action, cannot <hi>imprimere in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delebilem Characterem</hi> as Ordination doth. My meaning is, it does not, nor cannot convey an habituall power of Preaching, becauſe it is not the ultimate &amp; laſt action that doth compleat a man in his Miniſteriall Office. 2 It exceeds the end of this Call, which is ſuppoſed to be this, namely to give a teſtimoniall concerning his faculty in preaching, that others may judge, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> apt to teach, &amp;c. and not one or two, or three Sermons to men that are judicious and diſcerning (ſuch as they that try others for the Miniſtry are or ſhould bee) is as ſufficient for them to ground their judgement of a mans abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties upon, as two hundred.</p>
            <p>Hitherto Mr. <hi>Chillenden</hi> hath contended with reaſon, and is proved but an ill Logician, let us now enquire into his proofes from Scripture, and ſee whether he be any whit a better Divine.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Chillend.</label> 
               <hi>His firſt Argument is drawne from the example of</hi> Eldad <hi>and</hi> Medad, <hi>and</hi> Moſes <hi>words upon the report of it,</hi> Numb. 11. and 26. to 30.—<hi>The Spirit reſted upon them—and they Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyed in the Camp—And</hi> Moſes <hi>ſaid—would God all the Lords People were Prophets, and that the Lord would put his ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit upon them. Chillenden</hi> begins with the laſt part of the Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment firſt, namely <hi>Moſes</hi> his ſpeech, and afterwards preſſeth that example of <hi>Eldad</hi> and <hi>Medad</hi> more cloſely. I ſhall goe trace him in his own method, and ſee whether it leads to the concluſion pretended.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Anſw.</label> 
               <hi>Reader take notice,</hi> Moſes <hi>here wiſheth that all the Lords people were Prophets—not Prieſts or Levites (I meane ordained Offici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all men) but Prophets, ſuch as</hi> Eldad <hi>and</hi> Medad <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Moſes</hi> wiſheth they were Prophets, not ordained Officiall men: He need not deſire it; for they that had a ſpirit of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſy were thereby extraordinarily and immediately ordained of God to the work of Propheſying. For Propheſie was not a permanent habituall gift, ſuch as was in the power of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet to exerciſe when he would: but it was an impreſſion made in the mind by the immediate operation and irradiation of the ſpirit of God, ſtirinrg up a man at certain times to Propheſie, <hi>Ier.</hi> 42. 7. Hence it was not in the power of man, (who had the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:116472:8"/> power of Ordination in other caſes) to Ordaine a man to be a Prophet: as in the time of the New Teſtament it was not in the power of men, no not of the Apoſtles themſelves, to Ordaine another to the Office of an Apoſtle; but all that were choſen to be Apoſtles were appointed immediately by Chriſt, as the 11 Diſciples, and <hi>Paul, Gal.</hi> 1. 1. and <hi>Matthias, Act.</hi> 1. 24, 25, 26. This obſervation therefore is a nullity. Had <hi>Moſes</hi> ſpoken of a Function, unto which Ordination had been applycable, no doubt he would have wiſhed that they might have been ordained be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they had exerciſed it habitually, but ſpeaking of ſuch a work unto which nothing was requiſite—but the powring out of the Spirit, what need he ſpeak more then he did? 2. Let us apply it to the thing in hand: grant that he had wiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it to Chriſtians now living: I aske, doth he wiſh a Spirit of extraordinary Propheſy (ſuch as theirs was, as I ſhall prove a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non) or of ordinary Propheſy, ſuch as is common in theſe dayes of the New Teſtament, if extraordinary, then he had wiſhed that which no Chriſtian could have taken hold of, for a ſpirit of extraordinary Propheſy hath not been in the world ſince the Scriptures were perfected: if ordinary, then it makes for us, for then he wiſhes ſuch a Spirit as doth not exclude, but include Ordination, the Scripture acknowledging no Prophets in our dayes but Ordained Preachers, unleſſe it be thoſe falſe Prophets, and falſe Teachers which the Apoſtle ſpeakes of, 2 <hi>Pet. 2. 1. 1 Iohn</hi> 4 1. For my part I judge he ſpeakes of ſuch a ſpirit which himſelfe had, and which was then powred down upon <hi>Eldad</hi> and <hi>Medad,</hi> which was extraordinary, and therefore not applicable to us. 3. The ſpeech it ſelfe is to be underſtood as it is uttered, not indicatively but optatively. For <hi>Moſes</hi> doth not wiſh abſolutely that all the Lords people were Prophets, but <hi>quantum adſe,</hi> as for his part, he envyed no man that had the Spirit as well as himſelfe, nor would he have his ſervant <hi>Joſhua,</hi> or any man elſe to envy for his ſake, but he wiſheth all good to all men as it might be expedient for them. This is the plain meaning of the place, as he that reads may quickly underſtand, The like ſpeech hath <hi>Paul, 1 Cor. 14. 5. I would that yee all ſpake with Tongues,</hi> yet he ſaies before, <hi>Chap. 12. 29, 30. Are all Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets? Doe all ſpeak with Tongues?</hi> His meaning is, (the ſame with <hi>Moſes</hi>) he wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d not that the dignity of his perſon ſhould
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:116472:9"/> ſtand in the way, or bee any hinderance of others from parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king in the like gift. <hi>q. d.</hi> As for my part I can eaſily beare, yea I wiſh that that gift of Propheſy which is in me, were common unto all, nor will I have any man forbid for my ſake: and this I am perſwaded is the ſincere deſire of every faithfull Miniſter, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven of the moſt eminent, that your ſelfe (Mr. <hi>Chillenden</hi>) and all Chriſtians might have the ſame ſpirituall gifts which they have, if it might ſtand with the will of God and order in the Church. But what then? Is this any ground for a man to run before hee is ſent? <hi>Jer.</hi> 23. 21. But <hi>Chillenden</hi> (it ſeemes) doth judge the giving of the Spirit a ſufficient ſending. For thus it followeth.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Chill.</label> 
               <hi>That which made them Prophets was the Lords putting his ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit on them. Why then ſhould not men now, to whom God hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven of his ſpirit, with gifts, utterance, and knowledge be Prophets and Preachers?—The gifts of God are not given to be hidden under a Buſhell, or to be kept in a Napkin, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Anſw.</label> Doubtleſſe the Lords putting of his Spirit on them, made them Prophets; but this powring out of the Spirit did eminent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly include Ordination, or that which was equivalent or tranſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent to it, even an impulſive command from the Spirit which they could nor reſiſt, <hi>Amos 3. 8. The Lord hath ſpoken, who can but Propheſy?</hi> Yea, I conceive that the Spirit ſo over-powred them, as that they were not maſters of their own words and geſtures, but were acted by a ſecret Spirituall violence, even a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove themſelves to an high and extraordinary ſublimity of ſpeech, and inſolency of geſture, to the aſtoniſhment of thoſe that beheld and heard. Of <hi>Saul</hi> it is ſaid that when a Spirit of Propheſy came upon him, he ſtript off his cloathes, and lay down naked all that day and all that night, 1 <hi>Sam</hi> 19. 24. And in reſpect of thoſe inſolent expreſſions and geſtures which they were carryed forth to, that did they receive the Spirit of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſy ſuddainly falling upon them, it became an ordinary ſpeech in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> if they ſaw any ſtrange and inſolent carriage in a man (yea though it came from an evil Spirit) to ſay that he Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſyed, 1 <hi>Sam</hi> 18. 10. And we know that the Spirit falling up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on an ungodly man, ſo overmaſtered him, that he ſpake what he never intended nor had any mind to ſpeak. <hi>Balaam</hi> I mean. <hi>Num</hi> &amp;. 23. 24 Theſe Prophets therfore, w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> rather paſſive then
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:116472:9"/> active, in their Propheſyings: which I conceive to be the reaſon why the <hi>Hebrewes</hi> for Propheſying uſe the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in <hi>Niphal,</hi> the paſſive voyce, <hi>Prophetaties eſt,</hi> there being no <hi>Hebrew</hi> word of the active ſignification to expreſſe it by intimating that men were rather paſsive then active in Propheſying. Hence they could not uſe thoſe expreſſions and geſtures which are naturally moſt perſwaſive (as men in Preaching doe) but ſuch as they were, acted too by the Spirit, yea and what they ſpake, they ſpake from the Spirit, even divine miſteries immediately inſpired, wherein it was impoſſible for them to erre, though ſuch they might bee as they themſelves underſtood them not, whereas our Preaching conſiſts in an explication and application of the Word, which the ſimple and unlearned may wreſt through their ignorance, either to a wrong ſenſe in explication, or to a wrong ſubject in Application. And laſtly, the end of this ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Propheſy was to bee as a ſenſible ſigne of confirmation to them that received it, that God had called them in particular to ſome great and eminent imployment, <hi>Numb.</hi> 11. 16, 17. Hence tis ſaid <hi>verſe 25. They Propheſyed and ceaſed not:</hi> ſo the <hi>Chaldee</hi> tranſlateth it, but the <hi>Hebrew</hi> word is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> they added not. <hi>viz.</hi> to Propheſy any more (as <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ut.</hi> 5. 22. Theſe words hee ſpake, and hee added no more) intimating that then indeed they Propheſyed, but not from thenceforth continually; becauſe the Spirit was given them but as a temporary gift and miracle for confirmation of their Office. As unto <hi>Saul, 1 Sam.</hi> 10. 6. and <hi>Caiaphas</hi> the High Prieſt. <hi>John</hi> 11. 50, 51, 52. Now lay all theſe together, and it will appeare that in efficient, mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, forme, and end the Propheſying ſpoken of, <hi>Num.</hi> 11. was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary: and therefore <hi>Chillendens</hi> inference from that to ours is moſt notoriouſly inconſequent. Put it briefly in ſome forme: <hi>Eldad</hi> and <hi>Medad</hi> having the Spirit did propheſy. Therefore they that have the Spirit now may forthwith pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſy. No more but up and ride. Becauſe they propheſyed <hi>de facto,</hi> (for they could not chooſe) does it follow that every ſpirituall man may now doe it <hi>de jure?</hi> They ſpake by the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſion of the Spirit (which impulſion was an authoritative ſending or calling) doth it therefore follow that they who are onely gifted, and have no ſuch extraordinary impulſion, may propheſy, though not called thereto by the Church? They ſpake
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:116472:10"/> ſpirituall myſteries immediately inſpired, and therefore could not erre: doth it therefore follow, that any private gifted Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian may undertake publiquely and with all authority to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound and apply the Word, which in theſe dayes (Propheſyes and Viſions being ceaſed) cannot bee done, as may bee moſt for edifying, without ſome inſight into the Logick, Grammar and Rhetorique, which are, none of them; any part of thoſe gifts, that <hi>Chillenden</hi> acknowledgeth to bee requiſite to make a man able for the worke of the Miniſtery. If the Apoſtles and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets in writing the Scriptures have laid Arguments and words together, it is requiſite for the better underſtanding of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, that a man bee able to take their Arguments and words a ſunder, which how it can bee done, without ſome inſight into Logick and Grammar, I have neither Logick enough to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, nor Grammar to utter: though above all, I acknowledge a neceſſity of a ſpirituall illumination, and opening of the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding by the Holy Ghoſt, that a man may diſcerne of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall meaning of that which lyeth hid under the Letter. By all which (beſides that which is already ſpoken) it may appeare how invalid that inference is, which <hi>Chillenden</hi> makes by way of interrogation thus, <hi>Why then ſhould not men now, to whom God</hi>
               <label>Chill.</label> 
               <hi>hath given of his Spirit, with gifts of utterance and knowledge, bee Prophets and Preachers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Anſw.</label> Becauſe their gifts, (upon whoſe practiſe this Doctrine is grounded) were extraordinary, and therefore whether they ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed them with, or without Ordination, it maketh nothing <hi>pro</hi> or <hi>con</hi> as to our preſent queſtion, which is to be underſtood of ordinary preaching. But beſides thoſe gifts carryed a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion in their hand, to every man that received them, that he might lawfully, and muſt neceſſarily make uſe of them to his praiſe that gave them. The extraordinary powring out of the Spirit in ſuch an immediate, ſuddaine, plentifull and powerfull manner, was equivalent to a voice or Call from heaven, and gave ſufficient authority for the actuall exerciſes of thoſe gifts. But as for ordinary functions, in the execution of which gifts were neceſſary as well as in Propheſy, there did ever concurre a Call from God either immediately, or mediately by his Church: without which Call, whoſoever ſhould intrude into the doing of the work pertaining to that function, was a falſe Prieſt, falſe
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:116472:10"/> Apoſtle, falſe-Prophet, falſe-Teacher. In the Miniſters of the New-Teſtament, it is perpetually required that there be not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (ability in reſpect of gifts) but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (power or liberty in reſpect of Call) in all the Miniſteriall actions they performe.</p>
            <p>And if the gifting of men did enable them with pleny-poten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy for preaching in a publique Miniſteriall way, I ſee no reaſon why <hi>Paul</hi> or any other being put upon it to ſhew their authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty by which they preached, ſhould alwayes plead their <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or lawfull Call, and not their <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or ability in reſpect of gifts, which they perpetually doe; and not they onely, but the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures themſelves put an expreſſe difference between gifting and ſending (the two eſſentials in a Miniſten) the one materializing him, the other formalizing him, as I may ſo ſpeak, as <hi>Joh.</hi> 20. 21, 22. Firſt he ſends them (<hi>As my Father hath ſent me, ſo ſend I you</hi>) then he gifts them, <hi>Receive you the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> Ier. 1. 5. <hi>I have ſeparated thee, &amp;c.</hi> There's his ſending, and <hi>ver. 9. The Lord put forth his hand and touched my mouth:</hi> there's his gifting. <hi>Iſayah</hi> is gifted, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 6. 6, 7. but withall he is ſent <hi>v.</hi> 8, 9. ſo <hi>Ezekiel</hi> chap. 2. 2. <hi>cum</hi> ver. 3. So every Preacher of the Goſpel muſt be gifted, 1 <hi>Tim. 3. 2. Apt to teach.</hi> And yet withall he muſt be ſent, <hi>Rom. 10. 15. How ſhall they Preach unleſſe they be ſent?</hi> which ſending (though the Lieutenant will have it to be by infuſion of gifts, and that without any reaſon alleadged, or any thing like it, as may be ſeene in his Book Pag, 23.) muſt needs import an authoritative miſſion <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> according to the cleere etymo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy of the Greek word; which manifeſtly alludes to the name of an Apoſtle, a name given by Chriſt himſelf to them who were firſt ſent by his command to preach the Goſpel, <hi>Luke</hi> 6. 13. And it ſignifies one that is ſent, (not any way) but as the Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dours of Princes uſe to be ſent with their maſters mandates. This is alſo cleer by the very letter of the Text. For they that are ſent are they that bring the glad tydings of Salvation: And who are they? The watchmen ſaith <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> in the place from whence theſe words are borrowed, Iſa. 52. 8.) who in Hebrew are called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in Greek <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> which is the very ſimple word by which the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle Cals the Elders of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> (who were ordained Officers) and in them all the Miniſters of the Goſpel to the worlds end, <hi>Act. 20. 28.—Over which the Holy Ghoſt hath made you over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeers,</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:116472:11"/> or Watch-men, as they are called in <hi>Jſaiah:</hi> To ſay no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing at this time, that it is a manifeſt abuſe of the word [ſend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing] to interpret it of ſending by gifts infuſed; in which ſenſe, if <hi>Chillenden</hi> will undertake to ſhew where it is taken but once in all the whole Scripture: I will undertake to ſhew that it is taken above a hundred times in that ſenſe which I now contend for. But of this place more hereafter. In the meane time I ſuppoſe this laſt conſequence is ſufficiently battered, partly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Spirit of Propheſy, ſpoken of, <hi>Numb.</hi> 15. carryed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long with it an impulſive command, or immediate Call from God: and partly becauſe the Propheſy it ſelfe was extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and therefore cannot be compared in any due proportion with our Preaching, that from the requiſites or non-requiſites into the one, we may inferre the requiſites or non-requiſites to the other, no more then we may argue thus. Mr. <hi>Chillenden</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing unordained doth fight: therefore being unordained he may Preach.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Chill.</label> But let us ſee what followes. <hi>The gifts of God are not given to be hid under a Buſhell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Anwſ.</label> From hence our Saviour infers that the Miniſters of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, (whom he then ſent into the world to Preach) ſhould cauſe their light to ſhine forth before men, <hi>Matth</hi> 5. 16. What is this to privat gifted Chriſtians? A Candle is lighted to be ſet in a Candleſtick. The Candleſtick in the Reddition muſt be the Church, as <hi>Rev.</hi> 1. 12, 13. They that are ſet in a Candleſtick pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionably, are the Miniſters of the Goſpel, who ſhine forth (more eminently) as Lights in the Church. They muſt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, firſt be ſet in the Candleſtick, before they can give light to them that are round about. And how is that done? By being gifted and doubtleſſe not ſo onely, <hi>Act. 13. 47. So hath the Lord commanded us, ſaying, I have ſet thee to be a light to the Gentiles, &amp;c. Cor.</hi> 12. 28. God hath ſent in his Church (not gifted men) but Officers, Apoſtles, &amp;c. And our Saviour ſpeaking the ſame parable, <hi>Luke</hi> 11. does put an accurate diſtinction between the light of his Miniſters, and the light of eminent gifted Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans; of the former he ſayes that they are ſet in the Church (or Candleſtick) that they may give light unto others, ver. 33. And of them that receive this light, he ſaith they are thereby enlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, not ſo much to enlighten others, (though that alſo they
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:116472:11"/> ought to do in their place) as to make themſelves lightſome and glorious in the Church, ver. 36.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Chill.</label> 
               <hi>Talents muſt not be hid in a Napkin.</hi> 
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Anſw.</label> What then? Therefore every man may improve his Talent in a diſorderly way. This is fine reaſoning, peradventure a ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject in ſome kingdome may be every way better qualified for the well managing of the Scepter, then the King himſelfe: may he therefore take upon him to dethrone his lawfull King, and ſet up himſelf in his place? A woman may poſſibly have more wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom then her husband in the family, or more knowledge &amp; grace then a Miniſter in the Church: may ſhe therfore uſurp authority o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver her husband in the family, or over her Paſtor in the Church? the truth is, this excellent principle (miſerably perverted) hath been the darke Cellar wherin that powder hath been hid, which hath almoſt blown up all Government, both in the State and Church, and Army, and hurld all things into black confuſion. And I am ſorry that any of my Country-men (eſpecially ſuch as pretend to Religion and the feare of God) ſhould border ſo neere upon the Spirit of <hi>Corah,</hi> as to be of the ſame mind, and to ſpeak the ſame language, <hi>Numb. 16. 3. They gathered themſelves toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther againſt</hi> Moſes <hi>and againſt</hi> Aaron <hi>ſaying, you take too much up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on you, ſeeing all the Congregation are Holy every one of them, and the Lord is amongſt them: wherefore then lift you up your ſelves a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Congregation of the Lord?</hi> The ſame anſwer therefore, which <hi>Moſes</hi> gives to them, may I returne to <hi>Chillenden,</hi> and all others that make uſe of this Argument, <hi>ver. 9, 10. Seemeth it but a ſmall thing to you, that the God of</hi> Iſrael <hi>hath ſeparated you.—And hath brought you neere to him—and ſeeke you the Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood alſo?</hi> Surely he that hath a Talent, and employes it not, ſhall be eſteemed an unprofitable ſervant. Every gift hath its <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> &amp; yet every Chriſtian muſt remember that he hath his <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Rom.</hi> 12 4. his own proper work, in the performance of which he ought to abide with God, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7. 24. Can the hand do no ſervice in the body, becauſe it is not the head? In Fine, if there be any man in the Church, that hath the ſpirit of Grace, govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, wiſdome and utterance, whereby he is fitted to preach the Goſpel, though he hath not that meaſure of knowledge in languages and other Arts, as were deſireable, yet if he be ſound in Faith, in Doctrine, and in manners, he ſhall do a work accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:116472:12"/> to God, and the whole Church will thank him, if he ſhall deſire the Office of a Biſhop, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. 1. ſuffer himſelfe to be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, <hi>ver.</hi> 10. and (being approved) to be ordained by the lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on of hands, <hi>chap.</hi> 5. 22. And I am apt to think that no man who doth ſincerely intend to preach the word of truth, as it is in <hi>Jeſus,</hi> and affects not an unwarrantable liberty of preaching when he liſt, and deſiſting when he liſt (which being ordained he may not doe) I ſay I am apt to think hee cannot really ſtick at that order of admiſſion and entrance into the Miniſtery, to which the Scripture gives ſuch a cleere and abundant Teſtimony. And thus much for the firſt Argument, and for all the pieces of Arguments which are here and there, immethodically ſcattered up and down, which are neither ſufficient to prove the whole ſcope of the Author, nor yet have any dependance on any pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of the grand Arguments: As for the two objections which <hi>Chillenden</hi> propoſeth to himſelfe, and anſwereth, let him that ownes them make them good: for my part I would be loath to defend a truth of GOD with ſuch objections: though in the latter of the two, I conceive there is more ſtrength then <hi>Chillen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den</hi> is aware of, if it be well pointed. I ſhall ſay nothing to it now, becauſe I ſhall have occaſion to make it good anon; onely this I cannot but obſerve once for all, that this Lieutenant is very good at making <hi>Jack a Lents,</hi> and then inſulting over them with drawn ſword, here I could have thee, and there I could have thee. I preſume no judicious man could ever have it in his mind to make ſuch ſlender objections as I often meet with in this little Pamphlet, and therefore I ſuppoſe they are egges of his own hatching. But let us paſſe them over, and come on to the next Argument.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Chillend.</label> 2 <hi>Chron. 17. 7, 8, 9. The Princes of</hi> Judah (<hi>who were no ordained Miniſters) Preached the Law to the people.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Anſw.</label> I cannot beleive our Lieutenant read this Scripture over twice. The text ſaies expreſſely that the Prieſts and Levites prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched. For thus runs the words v. 8 9. with them he ſent Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vites, even <hi>Shemaiah,</hi> &amp;c. and with them <hi>Eliſham</hi> and <hi>Iehoram Prieſts.</hi> And they taught in Iudah, and had the book of the Law of the Lord with them. Here is not one word of the Princes preaching: It is ſaid indeed <hi>ver.</hi> 7. that the King ſent to his Princes to teach in the Cityes of Iudah. The Hebrew
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:116472:12"/> word is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in pyhell <hi>ad faciendumdiſcere</hi> to make them to learne, or to ſee them taught, to wit, by others, as <hi>Aſhpenaz</hi> is commanded togather ſome of the children of Iſrael together <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> to teach them the Language of <hi>Caldea;</hi> Is it imaginable that <hi>Aſhpenaz</hi> the chiefe of all the Noble men in the kingdom did teach them himſelfe? doubtleſſe he did it by others, as theſe Princes alſo did, and ſo Rabbi <hi>Solomon Iarchi</hi> expounds it. It was proper (ſaith he) to the Prieſts and Levites to teach and inſtruct, but the Princes went with them, leaſt they ſhould have rebelled againſt their words, that they might com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell them to obey, &amp;c. what a monſtrous abuſe of Scripture is this to interpret it againſt the very Letter of the text?</p>
            <p>
               <label>Chill.</label> 
               <hi>It is evident by the writings of</hi> Moſes <hi>and the Prophets, that any of their wiſe men might teach though not ordayned.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Anſw.</label> Hereof we have not one word of proofe, beſides. Luk. 2. 46. in the margent (as if <hi>Luke</hi> were either <hi>Moſes</hi> or one of the Prophets) where he relates that Chriſt being but 12. yeeres old diſputed in the temple with the Doctours, Was Chriſt one of the wiſe men? or is every diſputation a Sermon? or were thoſe Doctours intruders doing what they did without authority? Doth not Chriſt ſay of them, that they ſate in <hi>Moſes</hi> ſeate? Matth. 23. 2. For my part I judge them to be profeſſors of Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity or Tutors, who were wont to inſtruct younger men at cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine ſtate-ſeaſons (anſwereable to our Termes) Act. 22. 3. For which end they lived together in a Colledge. 2 Kings 22. 14. The Tutors and inſtructors being therefore called Fathers. 1 Sam. 10. 12. and the Scholars ſons of the Prophets. 2 Kings 2. 15. As to that which <hi>Chillenden</hi> urgeth farther from the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of <hi>Iehoſaphat, Hezekiah, Nehemia,</hi> &amp;c. we give this Short anſwer. That what they ſpake was either a judicicall charge, (which every Judge may give to the grand Jury) as <hi>Jehoſhaphat, 2 Chron.</hi> 19. or 2 a Propheticall, or 3 a Magiſtraticall act, and ſo not precedentiall to private Chriſtians. For a Magiſtrate by ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of his Office hath a ſpirituall power (though not an Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſticall or Church power) to pray, exhort, and bleſſe the people, and to make uſe of other naturall and generall mediums of ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall good, according to what I premiſed, <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4. For which end Magiſtrates had often (if not alwayes) a Spirit of Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy, as the 70 Elders whereof <hi>Eldad</hi> and <hi>Medad</hi> were two, <hi>Num. 11. Saul, David,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:116472:13"/>
            <p>
               <label>Chill.</label> 
               <hi>It was the cuſtoms of the Jewes to let men Preach who were no ordained Miniſters. As Scribes, Phariſes and Lawyers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Anſw.</label> Theſe at leaſt were Prophets, <hi>Matth,</hi> 23. 2.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Chill.</label> 
               <hi>Why did they ſuffer Chriſt to diſpute in the Temple?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Anſw.</label> Diſputation is no preaching. Nor doe I think that that diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation was in the Temple, where the ſolemn worſhip of God was wont to be on the Sabbath, but in ſome of the buildings a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the Temple, which were called by the name of the Temple.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Chill.</label> 
               <hi>Chriſt was permitted to preach in the Synagogues, Luke 4. 16, &amp;c. Though the Iewes did not acknowledge him to be a Prophet ſent of God.</hi> Ergo.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Anſw.</label> It was permitted him (eſpecially in <hi>Nazareth</hi> his owne country, Luke 4. 16.) becauſe he began not to preach till he was 30 yeeres old, and at that age his Majeſty, and the miracles which he wrought had made way for him: becauſe every man eſteemed him as a Prophet ſent of God. Luke 4. 14. and 3. 15. &amp; 21, 22, 23. Mat. 5. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>0. 21. And as for thoſe who knew him not (and for a long time he was but little knowne, out of his owne country) their permiſſion of him to preach argues nothing; for they did preſume that none would offer to preach but ſuch as had authority, and therefore when he taught before thoſe that knew him not, They aske him the queſtion plainly, Matth 21. 23. By what authority doeſt thou theſe things? and who gave thee this authority?</p>
            <p>
               <label>Chill,</label> Paul <hi>and</hi> Barnabas <hi>preached publikely, yet the Iewes tooke no notice of them, as of Miniſters ordained.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Anſw.</label> 
               <hi>Chillenden</hi> I ſuppoſe meanes the ſame which his Maſter <hi>Robinſon</hi> has writ before him, of <hi>Pauls</hi> preaching at <hi>Antioch</hi> Act. 13. 14, 15. To which we Anſwer, that it is falſe, that the Iews tooke no notice of them to be ordained Miniſters. For it was knowne that they were come to Towne, and the Ruler of the Synagogue ſent unto them verſ. 15. their fame there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore was great at <hi>Antioch.</hi> A whole yeere before this time, they had preached the word there, and brought many to Chriſt, where alſo were many other Prophets and Teachers that had preached the word both to Jewes and Greekes. <hi>Act.</hi> 11. 19, 20, 21, 25, 26, 27, 28, &amp; 13. 1, 2.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Chill.</label> 
               <hi>Act. 18. 24. to that end,</hi> Apollos <hi>was no ordained Miniſter, yet he preached.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:116472:13"/>
            <p>That <hi>Apollos</hi> was no ordained Miniſter, is ſaid, but not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved. For my part I judge he was. 1 He was a teacher in the Church of <hi>Corinth, 1 Cor.</hi> 3. 5. and that an eminent teacher, in ſo much as that his hearers had advanced him into a competition with <hi>Paul</hi> or <hi>Peter, 1 Cor.</hi> 1. 12. and preferred him before them. And there were no ordinary conſtant Preachers, but ſuch as were ordained, in the Apoſtles dayes. Yea and the Scripture intimates that he had as good authority to Preach as <hi>Paul</hi> himſelfe, though not given him in ſuch an extraordinary manner, 1 <hi>Cor. 3. 5. Who is</hi> Paul, <hi>or who is</hi> Apollo, <hi>but Miniſters, &amp;c.</hi> If the Apoſtles, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling himſelfe a Miniſter, in that place, argues ſufficiently that he had authority to Preach; why doth it not argue the ſame in <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pollo?</hi> the rather, becauſe the Greek word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> there uſed, is generally in Scripture, aſcribed to Miniſters in Office, or in Commiſſion, whether ordinary or extraordinary, 2 <hi>Cor. 3. 6 &amp; 6 4 &amp; 11 23. Epheſ. 3 7. &amp; 6. 21. 1 Theſ. 3. 2. 1 Tim. 4. 6. Act,</hi> 1. 17. &amp;. 6. 4. &amp; 20. 24. And why ſhould it not ſignify the ſame here? 2 The Apoſtle ſpeaking to the <hi>Corinthians</hi> of what eſteem they ſhould have toward the Miniſters of the Goſpel, adviſeth them to judge of them as they are; even as of Miniſters of Chriſt, and Stewards of the myſteries of Chriſt, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4 1. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> Now a Steward is ſuch a one as doth diſpence the houſhould affaires by Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion under his maſter. A Steward then of the myſteries of God is ſuch a one to whom Jeſus Chriſt hath (either by ordinary or extraordinary Call) committed the Preaching of the Goſpell unto his Church. <hi>A diſpenſation of the grace of God givon me to you-wards</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 3. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. Now ſuch a Steward was <hi>Apollo,</hi> as well as <hi>Paul, 1 Cor.</hi> 46. Therefore <hi>Apollo</hi> was a Miniſter in Office, called of God, either extraordinarily as was <hi>Paul</hi> and the Apoſtles: or ordinarily, by the laying on of hands as were Paſtours and Teachers. 3. It ſeemes that <hi>Apollo</hi> did Baptize as well as Preach, which yet farther argues him to be a Miniſter in Office (for though <hi>Chillenden</hi> claime authority for unordained perſons to Preach, by vertue of their gifts: yet I find not that he allowes them to baptize by vertue of their gifts) for when the Apoſtle ſaith. <hi>verſ. 13. Were you Baptized in the name of</hi> Paul? he adds ver. 14, 15. <hi>I thanke God I Baptized none,—leaſt any ſhould ſay that I Baptized in mine own name.</hi> q. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. Thoſe whom I Baptized, did I Baptize them into mine own name?
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:116472:14"/> that from thenceforth they ſhould call themſelves <hi>Pauliſts?</hi> Or did <hi>Cephas</hi> Baptize thoſe into his name, whom he Baptized, that they ſhould call themſelves <hi>Cephiſts?</hi> Or did <hi>Apollo</hi> Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize any of you into his name, that they ſhould call themſelves <hi>Apolloniſts?</hi> Yea (ſaith the Apoſtle) ſeeing you are divided into Sects, according to the names and number of them, that Baptized you, I am glad that I Baptized no more of you then I did, becauſe I would not be the Captaine and Ring-leader of a Sect. This (I ſay) ſeemes to be the plain meaning of the words, which cleerely holds forth to me, that <hi>Apollo</hi> Baptized as well as <hi>Paul</hi> or <hi>Peter,</hi> and therefore was a Miniſter in Office as well as they. Let us heare what <hi>Chillenden</hi> hath to the contrary.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Chill.</label> 1 Saith he, <hi>The Scripture is altogether ſilent in it.</hi> 
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Anſw.</label> Not altogether, for what I have ſpoken for it, I have ſpoken from Scripture: And if the Scripture had been altogether ſilent, yet were it nothing to the purpoſe: for there were many Elders of whoſe ordination the Scripture ſpeaks not a word, but leaves us to infer they were ordained becauſe they did the works of El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, As <hi>Criſpus, Tychicus, Titus, Demas,</hi> and others.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Chill.</label> 2 Saith he, <hi>We only find this of him in Scripture, that he was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed in the way of the Lord, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Anſw.</label> Whether this be true or no, let the Reader judge from what I have ſpoken of him.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Chill,</label> 3 Saith he, <hi>He could be no Officer in the</hi> Jewiſh <hi>Church, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he imbraced Jeſus Chriſt: nor in the Gentile Church becauſe he knew only the Baptiſme of</hi> John.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Anſw.</label> Bables; as if firſt there were no Church of the Jewes yet that embraced Chriſt and beleeved. 2. As if he might not be a Miniſter of the Gentiles, though he knew only the Baptiſme of <hi>John<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>expertus.</hi> He experienced onely the Baptiſme of <hi>John.</hi> That is, he was Baptized onely with <hi>Johns</hi> Baptiſme: and the Holy Ghoſt had not fallen upon him in ſuch ſort as upon the Apoſtles and other Miniſters of the Goſpell in thoſe dayes, which is ſpoken to his commendation, and the magnifying of the Grace of God in him, that he ſhould be ſo knowing in the way of God, and fervent in the work of God, though he had been Baptized only with water into the Name of Chriſt (which was <hi>Johns</hi> Baptiſme <hi>Act.</hi> 19. 4.) and had not received the Holy Ghoſt, as it was then diſpenced, which was Chriſts Baptiſme in
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:116472:14"/> diſtinction from <hi>Johns, Matth. 3. 11. He ſhall Baptize you with the Holy Ghoſt and with fire.</hi> 3. As if he might not be an Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſt as <hi>Timothy</hi> was, and ſo no ſetled Officer in any Church, but an itenerant Preacher to every Church where he came, which for my part I think is the truth, becauſe he travelled up and down with the Apoſtles. And ſo much for his third Argument.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Chill.</label> 
               <hi>Act. 8. 4. therfore that they were ſcattered a road, went every where Preaching the word. And</hi> Act, 11. 19, 20. <hi>It was the Church that were ſcattered; therefore, it was the Church that Preached: and all the Church at</hi> Jeruſalem <hi>were not ordained Officers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Anſw.</label> The moſt that can be made out from this Argument is this, That to Preach ſome times upon occaſion, when by reaſon of perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on we may not enjoy our own Teachers, and have no other helpe but our own gifts, is lawfull. But with what appearance of conſequence doth it follow from hence, that it is not onely lawfull, but neceſſary (for ſo <hi>Chillenden</hi> makes it) for a private gifted man (though not ordained) to preach, in a Church al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready conſtituted, and under the order of the Goſpell, where Miniſters may be and are ordained in a regular way, and their people may have free acceſſe to them? Neceſſity ſometimes is inſtead of a Call. Theſe that were ſcattered (grant that they were private Chriſtians) did not therefore preach becauſe they were gifted (for then they ſhould have preached before perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution had ſcattered them) But the preſent neceſſity was inſtead of an Ordination: at leaſt it was a Call of God for them to preach without Ordination, when by reaſon of diſturbances Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination could not be had.</p>
            <p>2. But the Text ſayes not that the Church was ſcattered a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, but (they all) were ſcattered abroad: which particular (they) refers not to the whole Church, but unto thoſe who kept company with Chriſt while he lived: and with his Apoſtles at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> after he was aſcended, even the 70 Diſciples, <hi>Act.</hi> 1. 15, 21. who were all, or moſt Evangeliſts.</p>
            <p>1. From the very beginning of the Book, the Evangeliſt ſets himſelfe to relate the <hi>Acts of the Apoſtles,</hi> together with the 70 Diſciples, (though he inſtanceth moſt in <hi>Peter</hi>) declaring how the ſpirit promiſed to be given them after Chriſts aſcention, did work effectually in their Miniſtery. Therefore here he obſerves the ſame method.</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:116472:15"/>
            <p>2. This is the more probable becauſe he inſtanceth ſo ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dainly and immediately in <hi>Philip,</hi> ver. 5. thereby ſhewing whom he meaneth-by (they all) <hi>verſ.</hi> 4. For had he ſpoken of a man that had pertained to a new company, of whom he had made no mention before, he would then have ſaid a certain man named <hi>Philip,</hi> or ſome ſuch expreſſion to give notice that he was di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recting his ſpeech to another and a new ſubject. But ſpeaking ſo immediately of <hi>Philip,</hi> it argues he is ſtill upon the ſame com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany; I meane the 70 Diſciples who abode with the Apoſtles and received their commiſſion from Chriſt, as well as the Apoſtles, upon whom alſo the Holy Ghoſt was powred down together with the Apoſtles, <hi>Act.</hi> 2. they were therefore men ordained by Chriſt himſelfe, <hi>John</hi> 15. 16. to go and preach the Goſpell. <hi>Chillenden</hi> grants that <hi>Philip</hi> was ordained, but it was (ſaith he) to be a Deacon, an Office that did not bind him to preach. Not remembring that the ſame man is expreſly called an Evangeliſt, <hi>Act.</hi> 21. 8. and that after he was choſen a Deacon: and ſuch as he was, ſuch ſeeme all the reſt to be, even Evangeliſts.</p>
            <p>3. It is ſaid they went, every where as (Evangeliſts were wont to do) preaching: <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> tis in the Greek; a word that is never uſed but for preachers by function, and though the word be a participle denoting an act and not a faculty, yet it al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes notes ſuch an act as is performed by vertue of an Office.</p>
            <p>4. They did not only preach, but it ſhould ſeem they did Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize too. <hi>Act.</hi> 8. 12. 16. 38. and though <hi>Philip</hi> be the man whois there onely mentioned, yet it is moſt probable that the reſt who were ſcattered abroad Baptized alſo. For <hi>Act, 11. 21. a great number beleeved and turned to the Lord.</hi> Now the manner in thoſe dayes vvas, to Baptize men ſo ſoone as ever they made pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of Faith, <hi>Act.</hi> 22. 16. and <hi>Act.</hi> 2. &amp;c. And therefore vve are to think the ſame of theſe at <hi>Antioch,</hi> that they alſo were Bap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tized; nay the rather, becauſe there is no other time mentioned vvhen, nor perſon by vvhom they vvere Baptized. Some of the Apoſtles vvere aftervvards ſent dovvn to themfrom <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> not to Baptize them, but rather to confirm, &amp; give the holy Ghoſt to them, being already Baptized; for that I find to be the end of their undertaking many other journeyes of the like nature, <hi>Act.</hi> 8. 14, 15, 16, 17. <hi>Act.</hi> 19. 3, 4, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>5. If theſe preachers had been private Chriſtians, dwellers at
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:116472:15"/> 
               <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and had fled only for ſafety, becauſe the perſecutio was hot in the City, and when they were abroad took occaſion to preach the Goſpell, is it not altogether probable that they vvould have returned home again to their families, as ſoone as the perſecution was ended? No man can deny this. Now I ſhall make it appeare that they ſtaied forth above twice as long as the perſecution laſted. For the perſecution began the ninth yeere of <hi>Tiberius Anno Chriſti</hi> 34. and it laſted till the time of <hi>Pauls</hi> coming to <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> Acts 9. 31. <hi>Then had the Churches reſt,</hi> which was about three yeere and a halfe after the perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion began, in the yeere of <hi>Tiherius</hi> 12. and of Chriſt 37. Yet they that were ſcattered did not returne home, though they might with ſafety; for three or foure yeeres after this time, <hi>Acts</hi> 11. 19. we read that they were got out of <hi>Canaan</hi> into <hi>Phenicia, Cyprus</hi> and <hi>Syria,</hi> preaching yet to the Jewes only. This was in the fourth yeere of <hi>Cajus Caligula Anno Chriſti</hi> 41. For in that yeere did <hi>Antioch</hi> receive the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, and then was <hi>Barnabas</hi> ſent thither from <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and thither he brought <hi>Paul,</hi> after he had found him out: and there did they two ſpend a whole yeere in preaching, which was the next yeere after this I am ſpeaking of; for then came <hi>Agabus</hi> from <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> and propheſied of a great dearth, <hi>Acts</hi> 11. 28. which fell out in the ſecond yeere of <hi>Claudius, Anno Chriſti</hi> 43. according to the conſent of Scripture and beſt Hiſtorians. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore from the yeere of our Lord 34. till 41. were thoſe Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples a preaching, that is ſome ſixe or ſeven yeeres, whereas the perſecution ceaſed at three yeeres end, more or leſſe. And yet we heare no newes of their returne, but that they went on preaching in <hi>Phenicia, Cyprus and Syria;</hi> which to me I confeſſe is a very ſtrong argument that they were not private Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, fled from <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> for ſafety by reaſon of the perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and ſo preached occaſionally and accidentally, but that they were Miniſters ſent abroad on purpoſe by the Apoſtles, and at that time the rather, becauſe they would not adventure the ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſall of all their perſons in one place, leſt the work of the Goſpel ſhould be retarded.</p>
            <p>6. (They all) that were ſcattered, cannot be underſtood of the whole Church, that is, of all the beleevers in <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> for the Text ſaith expreſſely, that the Church, that is, beleevers,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:116472:16"/> ſtaid at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> yea good ſtore, many houſholds of them, <hi>verſ.</hi> 3 and that when they all of whom the Evangeliſt ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth were ſcattered abroad, <hi>verſ.</hi> 1. And the truth i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, it is a ſenſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe thing to imagine otherwiſe: for if all the beleevers in <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem</hi> were fled, where could the Apoſtles be entertained? where could they find harbour and protection? that they ſhould be able to lie couchant, when ordinary private Chriſtians could not; yea, and to what end and purpoſe ſhould they ſtay when the Church (for whoſe edification, encouragement, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe and government they there abode) were all fled?</p>
            <p>7. Would not perſecution much ſooner take hold of the Heads and Ringleaders of a faction (ſuch as Chriſtianiſme wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> then eſteemed) then of their followers? Is it not probable that the Shepherd ſhould be ſmitten before <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Sheep were ſcatter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed? can any man then think that the Church was fled, and yet the Apoſtl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s continued quiet?</p>
            <p>8. That phraſe <hi>Acts</hi> 11. 19. They preached to the Jewes on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; and that other <hi>Acts</hi> 8. 1. That they preached in the Regions of <hi>Judaea</hi> and <hi>Samaria,</hi> ſeeme ſecretly to intimate what manner of men they were even ſuch to whom Chriſt had ſpoken. <hi>Acts 1. 8.——Yee ſhall be witneſſes to me both in Jeruſalem and in all Judaea and in Samaria,</hi> and <hi>Acts 13. 46. It was neceſſary that the Word of God ſhould firſt be preached to you.</hi> For which reaſons I conceive that they who are here ſaid to be ſcattered and to preach, were not private gifted Chriſtians, but Miniſters law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully called and ſent ſorth to preach. Let us here what <hi>Chillenden</hi> hath to the contrary.</p>
            <p>Foure things hee ſales, whereof the three firſt are upon the point but one, and therefore to them all I may returne one ſingle Anſwer. For whereas he ſaies, 1. <hi>The Scripture gives no hint of it,</hi> this appeares to be notoriouſly falſe, from what I have proved by Scripture concerning them. 2. Saith he, <hi>They are onely called the Church at Jeruſalem;</hi> which is alſo falſe, for they are not ſo called; and if they were called ſo onely, yet as long as the Scriptures are clear, that by (Church) we are to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the perſons forementioned, what matter is it for the name? 3. ſaith he, <hi>They preached onely upon occaſion of the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution.</hi> Neither is this true; for why then did they not returne home when the perſecution was ended? The perſecution was
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:116472:16"/> the occaſion why they were ſent forth at that time rather then at another; and if it were true, then ſay we, they did not preach meerely as guifted B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ethren (for then why preacht they not before perſecution ſcattered them?) but as men called by th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> preſent extraordinary neceſſity. 4. Saith he, <hi>Barnabas w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſent over to confirme them. A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſw.</hi> So was <hi>Paul</hi> ſent into <hi>Mace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donia</hi> to help, <hi>Acts</hi> 16. 9. They that were ſcattered went eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry where, <hi>Acts</hi> 8. and therefore <hi>Barnabas</hi> was ſent to carry ſome time amongſt them for their confirmation, which he alſo did, even a whole yeere and upward, <hi>Acts</hi> 11. 26. Some other objections there are (men of ſtraw which the Lieutenant ſets up to buffet) which we ſcorne to owne,</p>
            <p>
               <label>Chill.</label> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Arg. </seg>
               </label> Come we therefore to the next Argument, and that is drawn from 1 <hi>Pet. 4. 10, 11. As every man hath received the gift, even ſo miniſter the ſame one to another as good ſtewards of the manifold graces of God: If any man ſpeak, let him ſpeak as the Oracles of God, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Anſw.</label> To which we anſwer (leaving the Lieutenants Dandiprats for himſelfe to play with) firſt, That it is indeed every mans duty to improve the gifts of God in him for the benefit of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, provided that he miniſter the ſame <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> as hee hath received it; that is, in that way which is ſuitable to the condition of the guift he has received. But withal we aſſum that no man in theſe dayes hath received the gift of ordinary pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique preaching but he that is called, and that his very calling is a principall <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or guift which he receives from the grace of God, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12. 6. Having then guifts (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring according to the grace (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) that is given to us, which guifts in the words following he clearly interprets to be thoſe offices to which they were called. Is there no way of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municating guifts but in a way of preaching? Is there not as exhorting one another? <hi>Heb. 3. 13 a prevoking one another to love and to good works?</hi> Heb. 10. 24. a comforting one another with good conference? 1 <hi>Theſ. 4. 18. &amp;c.</hi> 2 Some conceive (and that not without ground) that it is a precept peculiarly di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected to Church officers. There is but one word in the text that ſeemes to make againſt it, and that is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> The Apoſtle would have them miniſter to one another, which word ſeems to extend the Apoſtles exhortation to all in generall. But for my
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:116472:17"/> part I ſee no reaſon why the word ſhould not be engliſhed in in own native and proper ſignification <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>ad ſuos,</hi> to his own, that is to thoſe that are related to him: and the neerer the relation is which any man has to others, the more ſtrictly is he bound to communicate the guift he has received from God to them for their good. As neighbours to neighbours, Maſters to their families, Parents to their children, Paſtors to their people, and generally every man, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>ad ſuos,</hi> as the word is uſed, <hi>John</hi> 20. 10. and the like in <hi>Mark</hi> 5. 19. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>ad tuos,</hi> to thine owne. Then the meaning of the Apoſtle here is this. That all Church-officers ſhould be ready to commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate the guifts they have received <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> to thoſe over whom God hath ſet them: which is the ſame adviſe which the ſame Apoſtle gives them, <hi>cap.</hi> 5. 2. Feed the flock of God <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> which is amongſt you. And for my part I am the rather incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to this interpretation, becauſe the Apoſtle having ſaid in the verſe next before <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (hoſpitall one to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards another) here preſently he changes the word (thereby intimating ſome change of ſenſe) and bids them to be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (not <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> to one another) but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> to his own. But 3. whether this be ſo or no, the place is cleere a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the preaching of private unordained perſons. For though the Apoſtle ſhould ſpeake here generally to all Chriſtians, that they ſhould communicate their gifts each to other for mutuall edification; yet he doth (as it were purpoſely) ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept a communication of gifts in a way of Preaching, making that a peculiar priviledge to him whoſe office and work it is to Preach, by vertue of his calling, ver. 11, Let him that ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, that i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, he whoſe Office and work it is to Preach, let him ſpeak as the Oracles of God. For <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in this place is he that preacheth, as alſo 1 Cor. 14. 34, 35. The generall Rule then is this, as if the Apoſtle had ſaid, I will that all men gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally improve the gifts they have received, to the benefit of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, as much as they may. Specially, let the Paſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ur or prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher, (the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) let him play the good Steward with his gift in preaching: and the Deacon with his in Miniſtring &amp;c. thereby intimating that when he ſpake to Chriſtians in generall in the former verſe, adviſing them to miniſtration of their gifts, he did not meane they ſhould do it in a way of Preac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing, and
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:116472:17"/> ſo uſurpe the Office of the Paſtour, no more then he doth allow thoſe who might be gifted for the Deaconry, to turne the Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con out of his Office, and play the Deacon themſelves, when he ſaith in the words following, let him that miniſters (that is the deacon) let him doe it as of the ability which God giveth.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Arg. </seg>6</label> We are now come to the laſt of <hi>Chillendens</hi> Arguments, wherin we doubt not but to find him as unſucceſſefull as in all the reſt.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Chill.</label> 1 <hi>Cor. 12. 7. But the manifeſtation of the Spirit is given to eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man to profit withall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Anſw.</label> I take the ſcope of this whole chapter to be this, namely, to declare the wiſedome of God in conſtituting and ordering his Church (the myſticall body of Chriſt Ieſus) and proportionat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing one member of it to another ſo geometrically, as that it abides in a wholeſome craſis and ſymmetrie, without ſchiſme and deformity; as from the order of the members in the body naturall, each to other, ariſeth the unity, conſiſtency, and beauty of the whole. ver. 15. 23. 25. 26. &amp;c. And this order in the Church is nothing elſe but a due correſpondency and aequipoyſing of inferiors and ſuperiors. ver. 27 28. 29. I ſhould therefore much wonder if this chapter ſhould afford any argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for <hi>Chillendens</hi> confounding error. As to thoſe words ver. 7. the manifeſtation of the ſpirit &amp;c. the meaning is that though there be diverſities of gifts, adminiſtrations and opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in the Church, ver. 4 5, 6. yet the manifeſtation of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit (that is the ſpirit manifeſting it ſelfe in thoſe extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry gifts) in what man ſoever it be, is given for this one end, namely the Churches edification: though the gifts be many, yet their end is but one: <hi>quid hoc ad Rhombum?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Chill.</label> 1 Cor. 14. 1. <hi>The Apoſtle writing to the whole Church of Corinth, ſaith thus, follow after charity, and deſire ſpirituall gifts, but rather that you may propheſy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Anſw.</label> We deny that the Apoſtles exhortation is directed to the whole Church: nay <hi>Chillenden</hi> himſelfe denyes it, and ſayes expreſſely (that the Apoſtle ſpeakes of propheſying, by thoſe who were enabled with ſufficient gifts) in this very place: and that indeed is his ſcope from the 28. and 29. ver. of the 12. Chapter, even to give directions to gifted perſons, in the Church of <hi>Corinth,</hi> and his directions are two, that they doe all
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:116472:18"/> in love (chap. 13. without which knowledge puffeth up chap. 8.) 2 That of all ſpirituall gifts they ſhould affect propheſy. But what is this to the whole Church? But the Apoſtle ſayes, you may all propheſy ver. 13. <hi>Anſw.</hi> Not all the whole Church; for he had ſaid before. chap. 12: 29. are all prophets? The Church is the finall object for whoſe edification propheſy is. Chap. 14. 12. not the efficient cauſe. But the Apoſtles mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is, that all that were Prophets might propheſy. For after he had given direction to thoſe that ſpake with tongues. ver. 22. 23. he comes to give direction to the Prophets for their num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber. ver. 29. and for their order ver. 30. and therefore of them is to be underſtood that which follows, <hi>you may all Propheſy.</hi> Now theſe Prophets were not private gifted Chriſtians, but men of eminency and authority in the Church of Corinth, and extraordinarily inſpired with a ſpirit of propheſy, as I ſhall now prove; onely I cannot but take notice how <hi>Chillenden</hi> fayles in the maine foundation of this his Argument, <hi>viz.</hi> that theſe Prophets were ordinary gifted believers, which I can no way aſſent unto for theſe reaſons following.</p>
            <p>1. It is moſt evident that the Prophets ſpoken of throughout this whole Chapter, are perſons contradiſtinguiſhed from pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate gifted Chriſtians For ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>verſ. 37. If any man think himſelf to be a Prophet, or ſpiritual &amp;c.</hi> Who are theſe Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall men? Certainly thoſe Chriſtians who did abound, more then others of their Brethren, in the graces and gifts of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit. For ſo is the word taken, <hi>Gal. 6. 1. You that are ſpirituall reſtore ſuch a man.</hi> And more expreſly in this very Epiſtle, 1 <hi>Cor. 3. 1. And I Brethren could not ſpeak to you as unto ſpirituall, but as unto carnall, even as unto babes in Chriſt.</hi> Here is an expreſſe oppoſition between a Carnall Chriſtian and a Spirituall Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an: the weaker ſort of Chriſtians being called Carnall, and the ſtronger and more able Chriſtians, who were men in under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, being called ſpirituall. To returne then to the place in hand, The Apoſtle oppoſeth the Prophet and ſpirituall man, that is the gifted Chriſtian, (as our Saviour oppoſeth the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet and the righteous man, <hi>Matth.</hi> 10. 41.) Therefore when he ſpake before of Prophets or unto Phrophets, he ſpake not to the private believers or Church-members in <hi>Corinth,</hi> though never ſo well gifted, but unto Prophets, ſtrictly and diſtinctly ſo cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:116472:18"/> who were a ranke or order of men in the Church, that was above the moſt eminent gifted Chriſtians in reſpect of outward ſtate and condition. And this is the more probable, becauſe the Apoſtle doth ſeeme expreſly to divert his ſpeech from the Church unto the Prophets and other gifted men in the Church, <hi>Chap. 12. 1. Now concerning ſpirituall gifts Brethren, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2. Propheſy was a gift of the ſame nature and continuance with the gift of tongues: as appeares by the Apoſtles perpetuall comparing of them together in this chapter. But that the gift of tongues is ceaſed now, and that it was an extraordinary gift while it was in the world, I ſuppoſe <hi>Chillenden</hi> himſelfe cannot deny. Therefore, how he can affirme the gift of Propheſy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o be an ordinary and an abiding gift, let himſelfe judge. 3 Propheſy was an interpretation of the deep myſteries of Scripture by inſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rationor immediate revelation, <hi>verſ. 30. If any thing be revealed to another;</hi> and <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 3. 3, 5.—The myſtery—which in other ages was not made known unto the ſons of men, as it is now revealed<note place="margin">1 Cor. 13. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> unto his holy Apoſtles and Prophets. Whence they that believe the doctrine of the Goſpell, are ſaid to be built upon the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Apoſtles and Prophets, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2. 20. And hereby is Propheſy diſtinguiſhed from Doctrine, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. 26. Propheſy being there ſignifyed by Revelation Doctrine noting an explica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the word, by comparing Scripture with Scripture, and by the Analyſis of a Scripture into its ſimple Arguments: which is the way of expoſition now in uſe in the Church. So <hi>verſ. 6.—unleſſe I come ſpeaking to you either by Revelation, or by knowledge, or by Propheſy, or by Doctrine.</hi> That is, unleſſe I ſpeak a Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion (which is Propheſy) or knowledge (which is Doctrine.) For what is Propheſy but the uttering of a Revelation? And what is Doctrine, but an uttering of knowledge? That know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge (I meane) which is attained by a ſtudious ſearch and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry into the meaning of Scripture. Wherefore it muſt needs be that Propheſy was no ordinary, but an extraordinary gift: ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary in thoſe dayes, being given but to a few; but much more extraordinary in our dayes, being given to none.</p>
            <p>4 From the ſame place it is manifeſt that Propheſy was not a gift reſiding in the mind by way of habit, but it was an impreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion tranſiently made upon the mind by the Holy Ghoſt, like lightning in the ayre: <hi>If any thing be revealed to another</hi> ſaith
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:116472:19"/> the Apoſtle. Cleerely holding forth thereby, that one Prophet might have the underſtanding of ſome ſpiritual gifted myſtery gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven him, while another was Propheſying: and that not by the help and operation of any faculty of his own, as his fancy, judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment or memory, but by Revelation, or divine inſpiration. Now I would aske of thoſe who call themſelves Prophets in our dayes, whether their fancy, judgement and memory do not help them to all the glorious ſublimated conceits, which they ſo much boaſt of (notions ſo tranſcendent that they many times leave all reaſon, ſenſe and truth many thouſand leagues below them) If they grant it, then they can no longer plead this prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of propheſying in the <hi>Corinthians</hi> for their patterne, it being of a more noble deſcent, even immediately from heaven, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the help and obſtetrication of any naturall abilities. If they deny it, and have the face to affirm that they receive it by imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate Revelation, then muſt I ſound a retreate to all that are men in underſtanding, and are not apt childiſhly to be toſſed too and fro with every wind of Doctrine, <hi>to the Law and the Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies:</hi> if any man adde to the words of this book, let him be accurſed.</p>
            <p>5. The Prophets in the Church of <hi>Corinth</hi> were not private gifted Chriſtians, but ſuch as had the power of the government of the Church, as ordinary Paſtors and Teachers. Yea, and thoſe very Prophets and the reſt of the gifted perſons (as I conceive) were the Paſtors and Rulers pertaining to the Church of <hi>Corinth:</hi> For that Prophets had a Paſtorall care, ſeemes undenyable to me, becauſe <hi>Act. 13. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas</hi> (who were no pri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vate unordained men,) are called Prophets: and it is a rule re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived without contradiction, that every ſuperiour order of Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters did conteine the inferiour. As for example, an Apoſtle was a Prophet, Evangeliſt, Paſtor, Teacher, Ruler, and Deacon, 1 <hi>Cor. 14. 36. 1 Cor. 9. 5 1 Pet: 5. 1. Act.</hi> 6. 2. &amp;c. A Prophet in like manner was a Paſtor, Teacher, Ruler and Deacon; for Prophets were ſecond in place to Apoſtles. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. 28, 29. And that theſe Prophets and other gifted perſons did exerciſe paſtorall Offices is cleere in this very Chapter. Firſt, the whole Church came to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether to heare them, <hi>verſ. 23. When they were come together, one of them prayed in the name of the Congregation,</hi> verſ. 16. <hi>To which they all conſented by ſaying</hi> Amen. They did alſo Preach
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:116472:19"/> the word and apply it to edification, exhortation and comfort, verſ. 3. of them that believed: and the converſion of the unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers. verſ. 24, 25. Moreover they had a Power of rule and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, to keep order and decorum in the Congregation<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> As for example, to enjoyne women ſilence in the Churches, <hi>ver. 34. Let your women keep ſilence in the Churches.</hi> The Apoſtle ſaith not ſimply let women keep ſilence, but let (your) <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5. 2. women: that is the women of your Church, which are within the verge of your authority. For do not ye judge them that are within? 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5 12. they had alſo power to make way for a Prophet to ſpeak, when he hath any thing revealed to him, <hi>verſ.</hi> 30, 31, 32. an act properly pertaining to the Ruler of the Congregation, <hi>Act.</hi> 13. 15.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> If you aske then, wherein did Apoſtles and Prophets differ?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> I anſwer, in this. The Apoſtles ſpake what they heard and ſaw, 1 <hi>John</hi> 1. 1. It being eſſentiall to an Apoſtle to have ſeen the Lord: and many Revelations they had of things not conteined in the Scriptures of the Old Teſtament, which the Prophets had not.</p>
            <p>6 But be they what they will be, their practiſe cannot be brought down as a precedent for private Chriſtians in our dayes to propheſy: becauſe the gift of propheſy periſhed in that age, when the Scriptures of the Old and New-Teſtament were accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed. For prophets were both in time and dignity before Paſtors and Teachers, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. 28. But the moſt honourable Office in the Church from thenceforth to the end of the world 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6. 14. is the Office of Paſtors and Teachers, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5. 17. therefore propheſy is ceaſed, being an extraordinary gift, pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar to Prophets onely, not to all gifted believers, Let us now heare what <hi>Chillenden</hi> ſayes to the contrary.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Chill.</label> 
               <hi>Firſt, ſaith he, the whole body of the Church of</hi> Corinth <hi>was not extraordinarily gifted.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Anſw.</label> Very true. For ſome were Prophets, not all. Therefore the particle (all) <hi>verſ.</hi> 31. is not to be underſtood of the whole Church.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Chill.</label> Secondly ſaith he, <hi>The Apoſtle forbids women to Preach, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they muſt be ſubject to their husbands: therefore he gives all men that were gifted leave to Preach.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Anſw.</label> If this Argument be good, it will infer a liberty for all men
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:116472:20"/> to preach, of what condition ſoever, as for gifted men; for may not I argue thus. No woman may preach becauſe ſhe is a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man; Therefore every man may preach: as well as infer this, therefore every gifted man may preach: unleſſe the prohibition made to women, reacheth only to gifted women? And by the ſame reaſon that <hi>Chillenden,</hi> upon that ſuppoſition of womens not preaching, infers a liberty of preaching to men, with this reſtriction, if they be gifted, by the ſame reaſon will I infer the ſame liberty for men, with this reſtriction, if they be ordained. But for my part I conceive the Apoſtles prohibition as it reach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth generally to all women, ſo it is intended ſpecially againſt wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, which had, or pretended that they had a ſpirit of propheſy, for ſuch then were in thoſe dayes, <hi>Act.</hi> 21. 9. though there be none now. And I am inclined the rather thus to think, becauſe the Apoſtle doth not ſay ſimply <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> but Ai <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> which particle (Ai) as <hi>Scaliger</hi> the great obſerves, is evermore deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minative, in the Scripture, pointing out ſome ſpeciall or indivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duall. So that the Apoſtle doth hereby ſtrictly forbid women though Propheteſſes, to preach in the Church, and that for a morall reaſon, (which a poſitive precept doth not ſuperſede) becauſe they muſt not uſurpe authority over the man. And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is the Church of <hi>Thyatira</hi> blamed for ſuffering that woman <hi>Jezebel</hi> to preach, notwithſtanding ſhe called her ſelfe a Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſſe, <hi>Rev.</hi> 2. 20.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Chill,</label> But <hi>Chillenden</hi> ſaith, <hi>that women Propheteſſes might Preach, and proves it from</hi> Luke 2. 36. Exod. 15. 20. Judges 4. 24.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Anſw.</label> Women, though Propheteſſes, never took upon them pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liquely to teach the Church. The places alledged do not prove the contrary, nor any thing like it. As for <hi>Anna, Luke</hi> 2. 38. The Text ſaith ſhe came in at that inſtant (namely into the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple) and gave thankes unto the Lord, and ſpake of him to all them that looked for Redemption in <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi> What is this to the purpoſe? Is a particular thankſgiving before three or foure people (and in all probability there were not many more, at leaſt in hearing) a publique preaching before the Church? And whereas it is ſaid, ſhe ſpake of him to all that looked for Redemption in <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> it muſt needs be underſtood privat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and from houſe to houſe; for all that looked for Redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> (which were many thouſands) were not then
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:116472:20"/> in the Temple to heare her ſpeake. And the Greek word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> which we tranſlate (comming in at that inſtant) ſignifieth that it was by meere accident that ſhe came to the Temple at that time: and therefore I do not beleeve that any of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> came thither to meet her.</p>
            <p>To <hi>Miriam</hi> Exod. 15. 20. I anſwer. That all that is ſaid of her is this, that ſhee and her maydens ſang praiſes together to God, though ſhee brought up the chore being a propheteſſe. And what they ſang, was no more then the very ſame which the men had ſang before them: for the text ſaith, ſhee anſwered them, ver. 21. compared with. ver. 1. But what is this to pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like preaching before the Church? Becauſe we allow women to ſinge in the Church, muſt wee therefore allow them to preach in the Church? Singing is for the edification of the members of the Church in particular, not of the whole Church collectively: therefore to ſing is not properly to ſpeake in the Church: for he that ſingeth ſpeaketh to himſelfe. Eph. 5. 19.</p>
            <p>To <hi>Deborah,</hi> Iudges 5. (which I ſuppoſe is the place you meane. I ſay the ſame <hi>Deborah</hi> and <hi>Barak</hi> ſang (which is no preaching) nor yet is it recorded whether publikely before the Church, or privately, as <hi>Mary</hi> and <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> each to other. Though I conceive alſo that in her caſe there might be ſome pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiarity, ſhee being extraordinarily raiſed up to be a Queen and Judge in Iſrael, and in that reſpect ſuperior to all the men in Iſrael, nor ſubject to any: and therefore not equally bound with other women, to obſerve the Apoſtles rule.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Chill.</label> But (ſaies <hi>Chillenden) The Apoſtle exhorts that the Church ſhould judge of the Doctrine ver. 29. If they had beene extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Prophets they could not erre, and then there had beene no need of iudging.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Anſw.</label> The Apoſtle doth not exhort that the Church ſhould Judge, but the other prophets: for as ſome had the gift of tongues, ſpeaking ſuddainly in a language they underſtood not, and therefore God gave to others a gift of interpretation of tongues 1. Cor. 14. 27. 18. ſo many might be ſuddainly inſpired with a ſpirit of Propheſy, and therefore others had a gift of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning of ſpirits whereby they knew a Prophet of God, ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from the ſpirit of God, from a miniſter of Satan tranſform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed<note place="margin">1 Cor. 12. 10.</note> into an Angell of light; for in thoſe dayes there were falſe
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:116472:21"/> Prophets gone abroad, who called themſelves the Prophets of God.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Chill</label> 
               <hi>The Apoſtle ver. 37. 38. exhorteth them to acknowledge the things hee writes to be the commandments of God. Could they be thus infallibly guided by the ſpirit, and yet muſt Paul call on them to acknowledge the things he writes to be the commandments of the Lord Jeſus?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Anſw.</label> Boys play As if 1. ſomething might not be revealed to an Apoſtle, and not to a prophet: ſeeing ſomething might be revealed to one Prophet and not to another. ver. 30. As if<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 2ly. the Apoſtle did not here put an apparent diſtinction be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween a Prophet and a ſpirituall man, <hi>if any man think himſelfe to be a Prophet or ſpirituall</hi> ſaith he, (as alſo a Prophet is diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſhed from a righteous man, <hi>Matt.</hi> 10. 41.) aſcribing to both a ſpirit of judgement: the one by a propheticall gift, for pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets could judge, <hi>ver,</hi> 29. the other by a gift of wiſdome, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the ſpirituall man judgeth all things, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2. As for that phraſe. (<hi>Let him acknowledge</hi>) it doth not neceſſarily carry with it the force of an exhortation, but of a ſimple affirmation, as it were ſignifying who are the true Prophets of the Lord, and who not: as in the ſame phraſe tis propheſyed that towards the latter end of the world, good men ſhall grow better, evill men worſe, <hi>Rev.</hi> 22. 11.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Chill.</label> 
               <hi>But</hi> verſ. 39. <hi>The Apoſtle puts them upon the uſe of meanes for this propheſying: which argues the gift was not extraordinary.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Anſw.</label> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> Tis in the Greek as <hi>verſ.</hi> 1. Be zealouſly affected to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, or zealouſly deſirous after ſpirituall gifts: and what he meanes by it, himſelfe expounds, <hi>verſ. 12, 13: Even ſo yee, for aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as yee are zealous of ſpirituall gifts, ſeek that you may excell to the edifying of the Church.</hi> Wherefore, let him that ſpeaketh in an unknown tongue pray that he may interpret. And this is all the meanes the Apoſtle preſcribeth, which is far from arguing that the gift was attaineable in a way of ordinary ſtudy and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry. Though we alſo acknowledge that the ſpirit of propheſy might be quenched, through the neglect and diſſoluteneſſe of him who ſometimes formerly had received it.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
